<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The enmitie between the two seeds: wherein is discovered, the subtilty and envie of the serpents seed: who rules in the man of sin, that is born after the flesh, and persecutes him that is born after the spirit; ... Here is also witnessed (through suffering the losse of all things) the immediate call to the ministry by the spirit of our Lord Jesus Christ, according to Scripture. With a testimony of truth to all those that desire to know the way to God, and a discovery of the deceit, with a testimony against it, both in rulers, priests, and people, that do profess God and Christ in words, and in their works denyes him. / Written from the light which the world hates, which they dwelt in who gave forth the Scripture, by one whom the world reproachfully calls a Quaker, not known to the world, but by the name of John Whithead. Here is also a declaration of the ground and manner of my imprisonment, and of the imprisonment of Marmaduke Storr: who is my companion in bonds for the truths sake. With a discovery of their proceedings against us at the two last general sessions holden for the county of Northampton. Here is also, a relation of the proceedings against Thomas Cocket of Dingley, ... the 13. day of the 4. month. 1655.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96407</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863754</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115968</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240907314</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E848_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204023</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863754</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863754e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 128:E848[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The enmitie between the two seeds: wherein is discovered, the subtilty and envie of the serpents seed: who rules in the man of sin, that is born after the flesh, and persecutes him that is born after the spirit; ... Here is also witnessed (through suffering the losse of all things) the immediate call to the ministry by the spirit of our Lord Jesus Christ, according to Scripture. With a testimony of truth to all those that desire to know the way to God, and a discovery of the deceit, with a testimony against it, both in rulers, priests, and people, that do profess God and Christ in words, and in their works denyes him. / Written from the light which the world hates, which they dwelt in who gave forth the Scripture, by one whom the world reproachfully calls a Quaker, not known to the world, but by the name of John Whithead. Here is also a declaration of the ground and manner of my imprisonment, and of the imprisonment of Marmaduke Storr: who is my companion in bonds for the truths sake. With a discovery of their proceedings against us at the two last general sessions holden for the county of Northampton. Here is also, a relation of the proceedings against Thomas Cocket of Dingley, ... the 13. day of the 4. month. 1655.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Storr, Marmaduke --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Cocket, Thomas --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115968:1"/>
            <p>THE ENMITIE BETWEEN THE TWO SEEDS:</p>
            <p>Wherein is discovered, the subtilty and envie of the Serpents seed: who rules in the man of sin, that is born after the flesh, and persecutes him that is born after the Spirit; which spiritual birth is here witnessed (by the operation of the power of God through much travel) of the immortal seed, which was promised and is come to bruise the Serpents head, and discover him in all his wiles where he appears.</p>
            <p>Here is also witnessed (through suffering the losse of all things) the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Call to the Ministry by the Spirit of our Lord Jesus Christ, according to Scripture.</p>
            <p>With a Testimony of truth to all those that desire to know the way to God, and a discovery of the deceit, with a testimony against it, both in Rulers, Priests, and People, that do profess God and Christ in words, and in their works denyes Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written from the light which the world hates, which they dwelt in who gave forth the Scripture, by one whom the world reproachfully calls a</hi> Quaker, <hi>not known to the world, but by the name of</hi> JOHN WHITHEAD.</p>
            <p>Here is also a Declaration of the ground and manner of my imprisonment, and of the imprisonment of <hi>Marmaduke Storr:</hi> who is my companion in Bonds for the Truths sake.</p>
            <p>With a Discovery of their proceedings against us at the two last general Sessions holden for the County of <hi>Northampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is also, a Relation of the proceedings against <hi>Thomas Cocket</hi> of <hi>Dingley,</hi> at the last General Sessions which was holden for the aforesaid County, the 13. day of the 4. Month. 1655.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:115968:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115968:2"/>
            <head>THE ENMITIE BETWEEN THE TWO SEEDS.</head>
            <div type="testimony">
               <p>I Am the light of the world, saith Christ, he that followeth me shall not abide in darkness,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 8.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12.</note> but shall have the light of life: and if any man will come after him, let him deny himself, take up his Cross daily and follow him; for he that in him will live godlily, must suffer persecution from the world, because the world knoweth him not;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 16.3. <hi>John</hi> 15.18, 19.17.14.</note> neither do they know those that are regenerate, and born again of his Spirit, and therefore the world hateth them, and persecuteth them, because they are not of the world: as I am a witness against them who am not of the world, but am hated, falsly accused, and persecuted by the world: as my Lord and Master,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.1, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.52.</note> and all the Children of God ever was, by those that made a profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of God in words, but lived in the love of the world: as they do who have persecuted me, and yet in words do make a profession of God and Christ; but are open enemies to him where he is made manifest in Power to testifie against their hypocrisie and deceit: as they have made it appear in falsly accusing, and making many grievous complaints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me which they cannot prove, as in their saying that I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115968:3"/>raile against the Ministers of Christ,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 25.7.</note> and the Ordinances of Christ, and against Magistrates: and they have sent me to prison (because I refused to take the oath of Abjuration, for Conscience sake in obedience to Christ Jesus who saith, <hi>Swear not at all</hi>) under the name of a wanderer, and a disperser of dangerous principles, and a breaker of the publick peace: who, as they say, am a seducer, and could not make it appear that I was sent to preach the Gospel; for if I could, they say, I should not have been sent to prison: but that is no new thing, but the same that ever was; for truth to suffer under the name of delusion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5.</note> and those that walk in it, as deluders, and hereticks, and disturbers of the worlds peace, and to me their reproaches,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26.</note> and false accusations are great riches: &amp; in them do I rejoice. Yet nevertheless, that no lie nor false ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation may rest upon the truth, to turn aside the innocent, &amp; cause those that be ignorant to stumble at it, and that those that falsly accuse, persecute, and seek to destroy the truth from off the earth, by their cruelty, in oppressing and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning the bodyes of the Saints, in whom the Spirit of truth guides: I shall declare what I was in the world, with my leading through the world, to the end of it, and what I do witness to it, with my usage in it, for witnessing against it that its deeds are evil.</p>
               <p>In the dayes of my youth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 23, 24, 25.</note> I lived without the fear of God, though he was a reprover of me from my Childhood: yet notwithstanding I hearkened not to his reproofe, but lived in pride and pleasures, sporting and playing, and vain idle communications, as all do in that state, who mind not the Counsel of God: yet was I outwardly restrained by the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my parents who feared God, from grosser evils, as swearing,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 56.4, 5.</note> lying, cursing and the like: which many children are suffered to run into, whose parents live without the fear of God, and by my parents was I instructed in the strictest pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Religion, that then was called by them Puritanism: yet notwithstanding I lived without any true sence, of my fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len and lost estate, until I was about 15 yeares of age, about which time I had a day of visitation:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.4.</note> and God who is rich in mercy and delighteth not in the death of a sinner, caused
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115968:3"/>light to shine out of darkness:
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</note> &amp; discovered to me my condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not by man nor outward means, but by the word which is power and life which then stirred in me,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8.</note> from which word light did spring up in me: and did let me see the iniquiry in which I lived, and that my heart was full of corruption, and filthiness, and lust to all manner of evil, and unrighteousness,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 59.2, 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</note> though I was outwardly restraiend from acting gross evils: thus I became sensible of my wretchedness and separation from God; and desires by the power of the living word, was begotten in me towards God, which wrought me, in some measure, into his fear:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12</note> and those things that I had formerly delighted in, that was evil, begun to be imbittered to me, and the fear of God caused me to depart from them;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.13.</note> whereby my conversation became blameless as to the world, but of the true knowledge where to wait upon God for redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the evil that lodged in my heart, and separated me from him, I was ignorant, but was instructed by my parents, to the use of means, as hearing sermons, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the scriptures, and the like which I much frequented, and so grew in knowledge beyond many my equals,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.14.</note> and as it grew, a secret pride grew, and my sin still remained in my heart, &amp; the wrath of God abode upon me, under the sence of which I groaned, but found no way to escape it; for though I had outward knowledg of God, and Christ, &amp; the promises; yet my will, and affections, and lusts, was not crucified:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col:</hi> 3.5, 6.</note> upon which the wrath of God abode, and in this state I continued until I was about 18 yeares of age (about which time I went into the Army) and I had often secret breathings, &amp; longings after God, but followed men zealously, whom the world called godly Ministers: who did speak much of faith in Christ, and of Gods free grace, &amp; of free justification, which things I did apprehend in my understanding, and did believe as the worlds professors do that the grace of God was free and that Christ died for my sins; and rose againe for my justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; and that justification was free by his blood. And here I got some ease, my outward conversation being blameless amongst men: but this faith was outward, &amp; the living faith &amp; living hope, which removes mountains,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22.</note> putifies the heart
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115968:4"/>and is an anker to the soule) I stood not in:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.9. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.20.</note> for the root of evil still did remain: and my heart was unclean and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me; so there was in me many doubts, and questionings of my state, and no true rest I found to my soule, but cossed from mountain to hil, whilst I sought it without, in observations, as hearing sermons, reading the scriptures, and the like: and in this unsettled state I continued, until I was about 19 yeares of age; and then the Lord appeared in love to my soule, that lay in the pit crying unto him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.21.</note> and did more enlighten my understanding, and by his Spirit convinced me of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: and he let me see that the kingdom of God was not in outward observations: but that it was within, and was righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 54.13. <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.6.</note> peace, and joy, and that all the children of the Lord was taught of the Lord Christ, and that He was the way to the Father, and that he was given of God, to lead his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into the Kingdom of God: And then by the power of God, the desires after righteousness was enlivened in me, and I was brought to wait in the fear of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Psa.</hi> 62.5, 6</note> on the Lord alone from whom my soul did find some refreshment, and his secrets was with me: and by his Spirit he shewed me, barrenness, driness hypocrisie, and confusion, in the most eminent teachers of the world,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> &amp; in all the formal Professors that then I was acquainted with, and the light of God that discovered their emptiness led me from following them; and my understanding begun more to be open,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.68.</note> in the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jesus Christ: and I see that he alone had the words of eternal life,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.15,</note> and I was weaned to him alone for teaching, and I had many openings in the living truth, and the eternal love of God in Christ Jesus witnessed to my soule by the holy spirit of promise,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13.</note> in which I did exceedingly rejoice: (and in this state I was about 20 yeares of age) but I being ignorant of the daily cross of Christ, in it to have waited upon God for the profession of what I did see and was promised to me;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.13.</note> the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent beguiled me under faire pretences, and said unto me, that I was now made partaker of the love of God, and that there was a perfect reconciliation to God brought forth in the blood of Jesus, and whom he loved once he loved to the end: and when the pure light that witnessed for God called
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115968:4"/>for purity and holyness; the serpent laid before me the failings of the Saints, and said, the best of Saints did cōmit sin, and that I could not be set free from it while I was here on earth, for in the flesh dwelt no good thing; but said he, that is no matter, for all is reconciled in Christ, and none can pluck thee out of his hand; and I lending an eare to him, in these plausible temptations, was drawn from the counsel of Christ, in carelessness, and forgat the loving kindness of God; and then my will got strength, and run forth again into pleasures, and wantonness:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8, 10.</note> so was I caried captive into <hi>Egypt</hi> where our Lord was crucified and the witness slain. And then that nature that was of the world &amp; loved the pleasures of the world, reioyced and made merry over the witness: yet a seed there did still remain, that did secretly reprove me, for my wicked thoughts, idle words, and vnsavory actions (though the world could not reprove me) and then the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of harlots, with the wisdom of the serpent, made cures, &amp; told me that that was but the Spirit of bondage that did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove me and would lead me againe into bondage, and told mee the Saints had liberty to take pleasure and delights in the world, and had the most right to its treasures, and told me that though I did act sin, yet God did not impute it to me, for he sees no sin in <hi>Jacob,</hi> nor transgression in <hi>Israel:</hi> &amp; that it was not outward workes that could alter the purpose of God, nor separate me from him; for whom he loves once he loved to the end and changed not, (but I had turned from that which he loved and it was in the house of bondage) and the mother of harlots sat decked in me, and said, she should sit a Queene for ever, and see no sorrow:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7.</note> and my knowledge I gloryed in, and could talk of experiences that I had passed through: but the Prince of the aire was head,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20.</note> and my soul was brought in bondage to corruption, (and in this state I lay near two years) and except the Lord had left a seed, I had been as <hi>Sodom:</hi> which seed sometimes disquieted the earthly spirit, and brought me in some measure into a sence of my condition, and did let me see that I was separate from Christ, &amp; had lost the divine love and vertue, that once I did injoy &amp; somtimes there was a secret longing in me, to be from whenc
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115968:5"/>I was turned: but the Serpent told me that that could not be done; for of my selfe I could do nothing, and that the Lords time was not yet come; for when he would have me otherwise, he would make me as he would have me to be, &amp; I could not resist him in the day of his power: and thus he drew me (from hearing the Counsel of Christ, who called for selfe-denial and holyness) to live at ease in the flesh, and put the day of the Lord afar off: in which state I had perished in my gain-sayings, but that the long-suffering, and riches of Gods love to me was unexpressable.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom</hi> 2.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And as I here lay in the house of bondage, the Lord in his love sent his faithful messenger who is called <hi>William Dewsbery</hi> (into the place where I resided) in whom God had raysed the witness, to declare his powerful word, and when I heard it declared,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.</note> and the cross of Christ preached, the witness of God arose in my conscience, and witnessed to the truth: and my understanding againe was opened, by the power of the same Spirit that did first convince me of sin,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.12, 14, 15. <hi>and.</hi> 12.47.</note> and I saw my self in the prodigal state, above the cross of Christ, and that I was the servant that had known my masters will and not done it, and the judgment of God took hold on me: yet a secret hope of mercy was raised up in me upon my return;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.18, 59, 20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.16. <hi>Hos.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.21.</note> and in this day of my visitation, I sunk down into the power of the spirit, that convinced me of sin and of judgment, and did resolve in the power of it to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto him, against whom I sinned. And no sooner did I returne, but in his love he did receive me, and put his fear in my heart, which caused me again to depart from all maner of evil: and he set up his righteous judgment in my heart, which took hold on the man of sinne: and a day of trouble, and great fear, such as was not from the foundation of the world, fell upon the earthly man:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.34.</note> and as I here waited, the word of the Lord came unto me and said, if I would bee his disciple I must deny my self and take up his cross dayly and follow him: and by the power of his word, my will was brought into the Cross, and I was separated from my former companions, and from the conformities of the world to waite upon God in the way of His Judgements.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115968:5"/>
               <p> And as I there waited on him, I did receive many preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promises: and that which lay in captivity,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> cried unto him for deliverance,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Psal.</hi> 18.6.7, 8.68.8.</note> and for vengeance upon the oppressor: and the Lord God heard the cry of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, and in his mighty power appeared, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of his own seed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.1.2, 3.</note> and to render vengeance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the oppressor: and the earth shaked at the presence of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> the great came in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance before him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.6.7. 8, 9, 10.</note> and the time of the Where that she should be judged: then that which had lain in captivity leaped for joy,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.8.10. &amp; 19.1.2, 3.</note> and triumphed in the power of the Lord, who judged the Whore, and plagued the Beast, and powred forth the Vials of his wrath upon the man of sin.</p>
               <p>Thus the Lord brought forth his own seed out of the house of bondage, with a high hand,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.</note> and a stretched out arm,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.33.34, 37.</note> and fury powred out upon the lustful nature that bondaged it.</p>
               <p>And I do witness, according to the promise of the Lord, that <hi>Sion</hi> is redeemed with judgement,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 7.27.</note> and her Converts with righteousness;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. &amp; 32.40.</note> and as he promised me whilst I waited on him in the way of his Judgements, he did write his Law in my heart, and put his spirit in my inward parts, that I should no more depart from him:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</note> and by his spirit he led me through the Law, in the daily crosse to the carnal minde,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19.6.14.</note> which is not subject to the Law of God, and there that nature came to be crucified, in which the enmity lodgeth.</p>
               <p>And in that state the Prophets who see Christs day, ministered comfort to my soul:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.11, 12. <hi>Psal.</hi> 78.15.16. <hi>Nah.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Isa.</hi> 40.4.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11.12.</note> and waters often gush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out in the Wilderness, wherewith I was refreshed and supported in the time of trialls, and in the trialls the pure grew.</p>
               <p>About which time I came forth of the Army, and the zeal of the Lord God appeared in the spirit of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in the spirit of burning, and the Mountains melted at his presence, and became a plain, by his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whose fanne is in his hand, who throughly purged the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115968:6"/>floor,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.15.</note> who is the Sonne of God, and was before the world was, but manifest in time, and born of a Virgin, and called out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> made under the Law, who led me through the Law: and is the end of it, in whom it is fulfilled.</p>
               <p>Thus was I led through the world to the end of it, who am not of it; for no more I live, but Christ liveth in me,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.6.</note> and the life which I now live, is by faith in the Sonne of God, who is my head, my Lord and King, and ruleth me by his spirit, which is my guide, glory; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal prayses, holy prayses be unto the living powerful God for ever and ever, whose presence is dreadful, whose power makes the earth to tremble,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Psal</hi> 6.34.9 <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Isa.</hi> 63.3.4.6.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1.11.12.15.16.</note> and puts her foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations out of course, who is arisen for <hi>Sions</hi> deliverance, and to the torment of those that hate her for evermore. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I having received Christ Jesus, am by him sent to preach the Gospel: and not by man, nor by the will of man; and the Gospel which I declare, I have freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not from man not by man, neither was It aught it,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> but by the Revelation of Jesus Christ: who by the working of his power hath made me a Minister of the spirit, not of the Letter, nor of man.</p>
               <p>And this Call is not contrary to Scripture, but the same that the holy men of God witnessed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.2, 3.</note> who was eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witnesses and Ministers of the word: and did declare the things that they had heard and seen, and was taught by the Revelation of Jesus Christ: and they by him was sent from City to City, and from Village to Village, to preach the Gospel, and they knew his voice, and was by his spirit shewed where the Lord had much people,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.1. <hi>&amp;c. Joh.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.9.10.19.20.</note> and directed whither they should go, and not by man, nor by the Scripture: as <hi>Thomas Pentlow</hi> called Justice, and <hi>Thomas Andrew,</hi> whom the world calles a Minister, who persecuted me, would have had me to have proved that I was sent to preach the Gospel in <hi>Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> by the Scripture.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115968:6"/>
               <p> And here they shew forth their blindness and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness; for <hi>Northamptonshire</hi> is not mentioned in Scripture, neither doth the Scripture call me by name, and say, go into such a place: neither did the Scripture call the true Apostles and Ministers of Christ, by their names, and say, Go to such a City or place: but the Lord Jesus, of whom the Scripture testifieth, he called them by name, and sent them forth, and they knew his voice:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.14. <hi>&amp;c:</hi>
                  </note> and the same Christ hath called me, and his voice I know, whom the Father hath revealed in me by the working of his mighty power:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 10.4.</note> and by his spirit was I commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to leave my near and dear relations, and outward imployments,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 48.16.</note> to preach Christ Jesus the light of the world to them that dwell in the earth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18.</note> which the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness covers, and to turn their mindes from darkness to the true light,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.9.</note> that lighteneth every one that commeth into the world, and from the power of Satan to God: and by the spirit of the Lord Jesus am I directed whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I shall goe, as the true Ministers of Christ ever was: and a dispensation of the Gospel is committed to me, not by the will of man but by the will of God, and woe unto me, if I preach it not;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.17.</note> but the love of Christ Jesus constrains me it to declare, and spread abroad in the world, that they may believe and be saved; and this Call is not contrary to Scripture, but the same that all the Ministers of Christ had as the Scripture testifieth. But I know that I shall be as one that speaketh Parables, and not be believed by the sons of the bond woman, that are born after the flesh,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.23.29.</note> who persecutes those that are born after the Spirit: for they are a wicked and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terors Generation, and seeks after a sign, saying (to those that are sent by the spirit to preach Christ crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.4.</note> and risen again the light of the world)</p>
               <p>If you be sent as the Apostles was, and have the same spirit that they had, shew us a signe or a miracle, that we may see it and believe: but I say unto you that seek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a signe, that all that had the same spirit, and by it did witness the truth, did not work miracles; neither was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115968:7"/>there any signe ever given, but the signe of the Prophet <hi>Ionas,</hi> to your forefathers the unbelieving Iews and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises, who sought for a sign, and persecuted Christ: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall you, who are in unbelief, and seek after a signe, have any given but the signe of the Prophet <hi>Ionas:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.4.</note> for you are an adulterous generation, as the Jews was, who sought for a signe,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.12.24.</note> to whom the preaching of Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus the light of the world, that lighteth every one that commeth into the world, is a stumbling block.</p>
               <p>But I testifie unto you, that except ye believe in the light,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19.</note> and walk in the light, you shall die in your sins, and the light that convinceth you of sin, will witness God to be just in your condemnation. And I to him shall be a sweet savour,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15.16.</note> both in them that are saved, and in them that perish, who am not sent to feed the wise of the world with knowledge, nor those that stumble at the light with a signe,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.23, 24.</note> but to preach Iesus Christ the light of the world, who was crucified, and is risen again, and the daily crosse. And this is to them that perish foolishness; but to those that are saved, the power of God, and the wisdom of God, and by them shall I be known and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed that be Children of light in their measure.</p>
               <p>And now to clear my Conscience in the presence of the Lord God, that the mindes of the simple may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and that those that are in unbelief, and perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the truth, may be left without excuse: I shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what I do bear testimony of,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7.</note> and what I witness a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst: he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear, and let him that is spiritual judge.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I do witness that Christ Jesus is the light of the world,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.12.1.9.</note> and doth enlighten every one that commeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, and he testifieth against the world, that their deeds be evil, and that is his light which makes manifest in the Consciences of you men and women,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.13.</note> the lusts of your heart: and lets you see that you should not live in covetousness, pride, enry, anger, swearing, lying, cursed speaking, drunkenness, lust, and uncleanness plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures and wantonness, dissembling, backbiting and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115968:7"/>and the same light that witnesses against these things, and discovers them to be evil, is the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the world that hates the light; and all you that do these things that be evil, you hate the light.</p>
               <p>You that be covetous and proud, you hate the light;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.20.</note> you that be angry and malicious, you hate the light, and all you that be swearers, lyers, and cursed speakers, you hate the light; and all you that be drunkards, lust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ones, lovers of pleasures and passe-times, you hate the light, and you that be dissemblers and Hypocrites, you hate the light, and love darkness rather, because your deeds are evil: and there is your condemnation,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.19.</note> that light is come into the world, and convinces you of sin: and you love sin rather then to walk in the light: and in your own Consciences and knowledge, the light will witness that your condemnation is just, and you shall be forced to acknowledge, that God is righteous,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12.</note> when he rewards you according to your works: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repent and turn to the Lord while you have time.</p>
               <p>And all you that do turn to the Lord, and love the light that Christ hath lighted you with,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.21.8.12.</note> which discovers to you the evil of your hearts, and calles for purity and holiness, and amendment of life, and in it walk: it will lead you out of darkness and your evil deeds, up to God the Father of lights and you walking in the light, as God is in the light, will have fellowship one with another, and the blood of Jesus Christ you will witness,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.5.6.7.</note> cleansing you from all sin, which none can witness, whose mindes are from the light, walking in darkness and the love of the world (though they may make a profession of Christ, and talk of justification through faith in his blood) with that minde that lusts to do evil,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> which is emnity to God and to Christ. Therefore all you that love your souls, love the light and walk in it; for every one of you have a measure which discovers in your own Consciences,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.3.</note> the works of darkness: though some object and say, have unbelievers the light of Christ, (I answer) yea, and it shines in darkness, and they hate it, and love darkness,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115968:8"/>rather because their deeds be evil: and the Counsel of Christ, from whence the light comes to such is. Whilest you have light walk,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.35.36.</note> least darkness come; and, Believe in the light, that you may be Children of light.</p>
               <p>And I do witness, that the free grace of God which bringeth salvation, hath appeared to all men, and it teacheth us to deny all ungodliness,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.12.</note> and worldly lusts, and to live soberly, righteously, &amp; godlily, in this present evil world, so by the free grace of God are we saved, as the Saints ever was.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.9.10. <hi>Isa.</hi> 64.6.</note> Which grace taught them, and doth teach us, to deny all self-works, and self-righteousness, which is filthy rags: and all you are found in the self-works, that lives in ungodliness, dissimulation, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie, professing God in words, but in works denies him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</note> and turns the free grace of God into wantonness, and stands in your own wills, which brings destruction upon your selves:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iude</hi> 4.</note> and God is just, who delights not in the death of a sinner,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.3.9.</note> but rather that he might turn and come to life, which life is in Christ, who lighteth every one that cometh into the world, with a measure which is sufficient to lead out of darkness all that love it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.4.9.8.12.3.19.</note> and is the condemnation of all that hate it, and turn the grace of God into wantonness.</p>
               <p>But some Object and say, If all have a measure of light that leads to life those that love it, and condemns those that hate it; is not this to hold salvation by works in mans loving or haring the light? and, whether hath man free will to love or to hate the light?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.10.19 <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.9.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I answer, No: man is not saved by his own works, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath he free will for to love the light of himself, but God hath first so loved man that in his free grace he hath given him a measure of light, and by his grace is the love to the light begotten, and mans own works and his own will denyed, in which the enmity and desires to do evil, lodgeth: and all his works are wrought in God, in the crosse to mans will, which crosse is the power of God to salvation: and this grace of God which brings salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which the love to the light is begotten, both ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115968:8"/>to all men:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. <hi>Jude</hi> 4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. <hi>John</hi> 5.40. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.13.</note> and would gather you into the love of the light, as Christ would have gathered Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, but they would not, and no more will you be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered now, who stand in your wills, but you reject the Counsel of God, and slights the day of your risitation, and turns the grace of God into wantonness.</p>
               <p>So here I witness, that it is by grace that man loves the light, and is saved: and by his own will he hates the light, and is destroyed: for God willeth not that any should perish, neither tempteth he any man to do evil, nor to hate the light: therefore put your mouth in the dust, and let the truth judge you, that stand in your own wills, which is enmity to God, and lives at ease in the flesh: in pride, pleasures, and secret lusts, sporting your selves in the day-time,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> and yet would charge the fault upon God, and make him the Authour of these things, when as he by his spirit, hath often reproved you in your own Consciences for the evil of your doings, which reproof you have rejected,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> the God of this world having blinded your eyes, because you did not abide in the love of the truth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.28.2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 8.11 <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.6.8.9.</note> but had pleasure in unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, which hath hardened your hearts, that you are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come past feeling, and in the reprobate sense, commits iniquity with greediness, and lives without the fear of God, doing despite unto his spirit of grace, because he indures with long patience and forbearance, your wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed works (which fits you for destruction) and doth not speedily execute his Judgements upon you, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you harden your neck.</p>
               <p>But knowest thou not, O man, that the goodness of God leadeth to repentance: and that his spirit shall not alwayes strive with man:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Psal.</hi> 15.6.</note> but he will render tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and anguish, wrath and vengeance, upon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of disobedience, who joyn to the Serpents seed, which is accursed and reprobate from God: and in that day of his power you cannot resist, nor escape the day of his wrath, which shall burn as an Owen,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1.</note> if you follow the Serpent, who leads you into Iust and filthiness, none
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115968:9"/>can save you from the wrath of Allmighty God: but you shall perish in your Abomination, which you have sown to the flesh,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7.8.</note> of which you shall reap corruption, and be punished with everlasting perdition from God who is pure, and from his holy Angels: therefore prise your time, and take heed to the light, that secretly reproves you for sin,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 1.9.</note> and it will bring you to repentance, and into the fear of God: but disobeying of it is your condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, remember you are warned in your life-time, all you that live without the fear of God, at ease in the flesh, who commit sin because grace abounds.</p>
               <p>And I do witness, that the spirit of truth, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth the world of sin, is sufficient to lead and guide into all truth, and doth convince also of unbelief, and of righteousness,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.8.9. <hi>and</hi> 10.</note> and of judgement: and here let the truth judge you, that say that the light which convinces the world of sin, doth not convince them also of unbelief; or that say, that the spirit of Christ, doth not convince an unbeliever of sin, or that say, that light which convinceth an unbeliever of sin, is not sufficient to lead into all truth, without the teachings of men; for Christ saith, that the spirit of truth shall convince the world of sin; and they be the world who believe not on him, and it convinceth them of unbelief,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.13.</note> and will lead into all truth those that are guided by it: and he that denies him to be come, who convinceth the world of sin; is a deceiver,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7.</note> and an Antichrist: therefore all people, take heed to that which convinceth you of sin, and calles you to repent and amend your lives, and lets you see secret lust, and corruption, and hypocrisie, and hardness of heart, and unbelief, and reproves you for it; for that is the spirit of truth, and you walking in it, it will not let you satisfie the lusts of the flesh: but it will bring a crosse to your wills and lusts, so will you witness the flesh crucified with the affections and lusts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16.24.6.14.</note> as the Saints did and doth, who rejoyced in the Crosse of Christ, and walked and do walk in the spirit, that leads in the strait gate of self-denial: and in the strait gate of self-denial
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115968:9"/>you must walk,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13.16.24.</note> and the daily Crosse of Christ you most take up, to your wills and lusts, or you can not be the Disciples of Christ, nor enter into the Kingdom of God, for the broad way leads to destruction, and faith Christ Jesus (who is the way to the Father,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.6.8.12.</note> the truth and the life and the light of the world:) If any one will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his Crosse daily and follow me, and he shall not abide in darkness, but shall have eternal life.</p>
               <p>And I do witness that the gift of God is free,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15.6.23.</note> and is eternal life, which life is Iesus Christ, who tasted death for every man: and I do witness that faith in his blood justifieth, which faith is the gift of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9.</note> given to all those that wait on him in the light; and the same faith that justifies, purifies the heart,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22.24. <hi>and</hi> 25.</note> and the blood of Iesus clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth them that be in the faith from all sin: and this faith which purifies and works by love into the obedience of Iesus Christ, is not a dead talk, and barren profession, which the world lives in: but it is living, and is a Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry held in a pure Conscience,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27.2.11. 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 5.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22.23. <hi>and</hi> 24. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> and it stands in Iesus Christ, &amp; Christ in him that hath it, the hope of glory: &amp; this faith is the victory, whereby the Saints overcome the world, and put off the body of the sins of the flesh, by the putting on of the body of Christ: and here the old man is put off with his deeds, and the enmity slain by the blood of his Crosse, and the new man created after God in righteousness and true holiness, which is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God that was in the beginning which is perfect and sins not, neither can he, because he is born of God, and his seed remains in him. You that read this, prove your selves, whether you be in the faith or no, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess no more then you do possess.</p>
               <p>For I do stand a witness against all you that make a profession of God, and of Christ, and talks of faith in him, and of redemption by his blood, and free justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and yet say, that not any can be made free from sin, whilest they are in this life: and do your selves live in sin, and in the love and conformities of the world; for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115968:10"/>you are they that say and do not,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.3.</note> and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Christ, and makes him a Cloke for your sins, and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his blood an unholy thing,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.</note> and redemption you cannot witness by it, who do walk in darkness: and your faith is dead and vain,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.24 <hi>Jude</hi> 1.16.</note> who are yet in your sins, and believes that you must live in them whilst you are in the body, and here you are found in the stoathful Servants condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that mutmurs and complains, and walks after your ungodly lusts: and say that you have not power to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.34.</note> and then sits down at ease, to eat and drink with the drunken, and so are over come with the cares of this life, and denies to take up the Crosse, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle preached the power of God to salvation,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.13.</note> and looke for a power to come and destroy sin, when you go out of the body; and you never to have your lusts and desires to it crucified in the Crosse:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6.</note> and with the light of Christ you are seen, to be they that put him to open shame, with your works of darkness, and vain imaginings, that none can be saved from sin whilst they are in the body,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</note> (when as the Scripture saith, that he is able to save to the uttermost,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18.22.</note> all those that come to God by him, and the Saints that did and doth follow him, was, and is made free from sin, and become Servants of righteousness, and have their fruit unto holiness,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.45</note> and the end is everlasting life:) and in this state, some of you that make a profession of Christ are found,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.9.</note> putting the day of the Lord farre off, and you I warn to awake and sin not; for the Iudge, stands before the door,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43.</note> and the wages of sin is death. He that hath an eare to hear let him hear.</p>
               <p>And I do witness, that not any Minister of Christ is made by the will of man,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1.11.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.8.2.4. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.20.</note> nor fitted for his Ministry by humane learning, nor sharpness of wit, nor by any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural gift: but by the gift of the spirit of Iesus Christ, which gift cannot be bought nor sold for mony, nor limited to times and persons, but is free: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straines him that hath received it, freely to minister it forth. And I doe stand a witness against all those that say they are gifted to Preach the Gospel, &amp; limits them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115968:10"/>to a particular time, people, and place:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jud.</hi> 10.11.2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3.18.</note> and there sells their gift for mony, for these are they that goes in <hi>Balaams</hi> way, and through fained words and high expressions, makes Merchandize of the people. And I do witness against all those that do profess themselves to be Ministers of Christ,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9.</note> and denies that he lighteth every one that cometh into the world, or that calls His light, which lighteth every one that cometh into the world, a natural light, and denys the immediate Call to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery by the spirit of Christ, and saies that they are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ministry by humane learning,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.42</note> and called and approved of men (for these are they that are disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of God) and causes the people to erre by their lies, in denying that Christ lighteth every one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, and in calling His light naturall, which light is the very way to God: and these are found building, without the corner-stone, and their building is <hi>Bubell,</hi> for they run and was never sent of God, and speaks a divination of their own braine-studdy,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. read the whole Chapter.</note> and not from the mouth of the Lord, and uses their tongue when the Lord never spoke to them, but they steale the word from their neighbour, and such the Lord is and ever was against, and he hath shaken his hand at their dishonest gaine, who do for filthy lucre runne when the Lord ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver sent them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15.16.</note> and therefore shall they nor profit the people at all. And by their fruits they are knowne, though they come in sheeps clothing, and profess them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be Ministers of Christ, yet do witness against them all, that abides not in the doctrine of Christ, but acts those things that the true. Prophets and Christ did witness against (for they are inwardly ravening Wolves) that do seek for their gaine from their quarter,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.31. <hi>Isa.</hi> 56.10.11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.2.3. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.5.11.</note> and beares rule by their meanes, and clothes themselves with the fleece, and feedes themselves with the fatt, and bites with their teeth, and cries peace peace, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares warr against them that <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> into their mouths and preaches for hire, and divines for mony: and such <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> these the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lord witnesses against:
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115968:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115968:11"/>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115968:12"/>as the Scripture testisleth, and I do witness against all those that profess to be Ministers of Christ,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12.8.7.8.</note> and receives tithes, which stood in the first Covenant, to be paid to the first Preist-hood: which Covenant was found faulty, and that preist-hood changed. And against all that sue people at Law for tithes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.40.</note> or for wages, to whom they do neither minister spirituall things nor temporal; for these things are contrary to the doctrine of Christ,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.34 2.33.</note> and the practice of his true Ministers: neither did any of the false Prophets, deceivers, or hirelings, ever sue any at Law for Tithes or wages, that we read of in Scriptures: and here you that act such things, with the light of Christ are seene, to out-strip them all in oppression: O blush for shame, and let the truth Judge you,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5.23.6.7, 8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.43.44, 45. <hi>and</hi> 46. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.12.13.</note> who profess to be teachers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and act such things: Ye generation of Vipers how can you that be evill, speak good things, how can you escape the damnation of Hell! that profess your selves to be Ministers of Christ, and abides not in his doctrine, but acts those things that he cried woe against: as to stand praying in the Synagogues, and have the cheifest seats in the Affemblies, and the upermost roomes at Feasts, and loves greetings in the Markets, and are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of men Masters (which Christ forbid) and layes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burthens upon the people, and preaches for hire, in a particular parish, and so becomes the hireling of men which cares not for the sheepe, but through covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, makes Merchandize of the people: which never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Minister of Christ did. And I do witness against all you that do profess your selves to be Ministers of Christ, and lives in covetousness, strife, and contention; swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drunkenness and faise accus<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, pleasures and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonness, lust and uncleanness, pride and headiness, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over Gods heritage.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> And against all you that have a forme of godliness, and denys the power (which leads out of sin) and creeps into particular houses, which you call Churches, &amp; there keeps people ever learning &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver able to come to the knowledge of the truth: which makes free those that know it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.32.</note> and walk in it; now you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115968:12"/>that call this railing against the Ministers of Christ, speaks against the Scripture which bears testimony to what is heare declared: and the light of Christ, will condemne you eternally from God, that are found in these practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that are contrary to Scripture, except you repent.</p>
               <p>But all those that are Ministers of Christ, I owne,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13.20.10.8.</note> and by their fruits they are knowne, that have received Christ and are by his spirit sent to preach: and abides in his doctrine, and freely declares what they have freely received, as the spirit gives them utterance: and walks in the spirit, and brings forth the fruit of it, which is love, joy, Peace, Gentleness, Goodness, Faith, Meekness, Temperance, Patience, Brotherly kindness, and the like: and these who are the true Ministers of Christ are no hireling, nor covetous ones, nor proud, self willed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.23.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent, headie, unholy ones, nor despisers of t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ose that are good, nor persecuters, nor false accusers, nor truce breakers, nor resisters of the truth, nor denyers of the power of godliness, nor creepers into houses, nor leaders captive of silly women, ever learning them and never bringing them to the knowledge of the truth: but the Ministers of Christ walks in the power of godliness, and goes from Cittie to Cittie, and from village to vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, preaching the Kingdom of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and enters into their houses that be worthy, and brings people to the knowledge of the truth, which leads out of sin all that love it, and these I own and honour, who give no offence in any thing that their Ministery be not blamed: but do in all things approve themselves as the Ministers of Christ: in much patience, in afflictions, in necessities and distresses, in stripes and in prisonment, in tumults, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in watchings, in fastings:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> by pureness, by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, by long suffering, by kindness, by the holy Ghost, by love unfained, by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the Armour of righteousness, on the right hand, and on the left, by honour and dishonour, by evil report and good report, as deceivers and yet true, as unknown and yet well known, as dying and behold we live, as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115968:13"/>chastened, and not killed; as sorrowful, yet alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joysing; as poor, yet making many rich, as having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet possessing all things; &amp; these that thus approve themselves, I own and esteem, and witness: but those are not known, nor approved by the world; but hated and persecured.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 28.15.17.</note> And here I charge you all, to stop your mouthes that do falsly accuse me of railing against the Ministers of Christ, and give over making lies your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, least you with them be swept away.</p>
               <p>And I do also own and witness the Ordinances of Christ, as self-denial, and the daily Crosse, love one to another, to do to all men as we would be done unto, and not to swear at all, and if any smite the one cheek to turn the other, and to feed the hungry, and clothe the naked, and the like.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24 <hi>John</hi> 15.12 <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.31. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.36.39. &amp; 42. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15.29.30.31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29.30. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.29 <hi>Psal.</hi> 37.28.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>John</hi> 8.35.</note> And also preaching and prophesying, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportion of faith, as every one hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Lord, and praying with the spirit, and sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the spirit, and with the understanding also, (as the Lord moveth) I own: and baptisme by one spirit into one body, which brings down into death with Christ, and into the fellowship of his sufferings, I own and witness: and the Communion of Saints at the Table of the Lord, where they feed on the living bread, and all drinks into one spirit, which makes them of one heart, and of one soul, I own and witness: prayses for ever be unto the Lord. But I know, that the sons of <hi>Hagar</hi> the <hi>Egyptain</hi> woman, that are born after the flesh, whose por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be cast out, and feed on the husks, will scoffe at the moving of the spirit of the Lord, and say ha, ha these people will do nothing but what the spirit moves them to; but I say unto you that scoffe at the moving of the spirit of the Lord, that you are they which <hi>Peter</hi> said, should come in the last time: but yet a little while, and the scorners shall be consumed, and you that turn from the spirit of the Lord, and work wickedness, cut off: but they that are guided by the spirit of God, are the Sons of God, and shall inherit the Kingdom, which fades not, and in it abide for ever: and here is a testimony of truth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115968:13"/>declared against all you who falsly say, I disown or rail against the Ordinances of Christ.</p>
               <p>But the Inventions and Traditions of men, I do freely te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie against: as preaching for hire,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.16, 30, 31. <hi>and.</hi> 32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5, 23, 24. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</note> a divination of their own brain study, limitting themselves by the hour, and standing praying in the Synagogues, for a pretence making their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers long, whilst they regard iniquity in their hearts, and are enercised with covetous practices, and acts those things that Christ cried wo against: and singing <hi>Davids</hi> Psalms in Rime and Meeter: As, for proud men, and men of strife and contention to sing these words (turned into a rime) <hi>Lord my heart is not haughty, nor my eies lofty,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psa.</hi> 131.12.</note> neither do</hi> I <hi>exercise my self in great matters, nor in things too high for me: surely</hi> I <hi>have behaved and quieted my self as a child that is weaned of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; my soul is even as a weaned child.</hi> And for those that live without the fear of God, and never came into any true sence of their sins, but lives in jollity, and wantonness,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Psal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Psa.</hi> 119.120.</note> to sing <hi>All my flesh trembles,</hi> I <hi>am afraid of thy Judgments:</hi> I <hi>go mourning all the day, and at night</hi> I <hi>water my couch with my tears.</hi> And thus poor ignorant people sings lyes to the Lord, whereby he is dishonoured; and these things, and sprinkling of Infants, (which there is no Scripture for) is counted the Ordinances of Christ, by those that know not God: but I witness against them, and against that which the world calls a Sacrament, where a company of carnal people that discern not the Lords body meet at a carnal table, to eat and drink carnal bread and wine, which feeds the carnal man;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29.</note> for these are they that eat and drink damnation to themselves: who some of them live in covetousness, oppression, and hard-heartedness: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in envy, hatred, rashness, self-willedness, and per ecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the innocent: and others in pleisures, drunkenness, lust, and undleanness: and others, in dissimulation and hypocrisy,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> having a form of god iness, but denies the power: and Christ never commanded you any such things as you practise and call his Ordinances, neither was they the Saints practice; for they dwelt in the light and life, and possessed the substance;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2, 3, 4, 5.16, 17 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</note> therefore cease from your Inventions, and Traditions, and walk in the light of Christ, which reproves you for sin, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115968:14"/>calls for holiness and truth in the inward parts:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7.</note> in which light is the unity and communion of Saints.</p>
               <p>And whereas I am accused of railing against and contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Authority, I do declare in the presence of God, It is false; for my soul is subject to the higher power,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> for conscience sake: and magistracie I own, which is the Ordinance of God, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the punishment of evil doers, and for the praise of them that do well; and those Magistrares that are guided by the light of Christ, which is equal and just, and act Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice according to the Law of God without respect of persons, I own and honour in my soul, not with flatteries and deceit, as the custome of the world is: but with submission to the Law of God, of which he is a Minister for good to me, who respects no mans person, but punishes the evil doet, and countenanceth him that doeth well; But he that is in the place of a Magistrate, and turns from the light of Christ, and casts the Law of God behind his back,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17.16.17.27.19. <hi>read Isa.</hi> 59</note> and respects the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of men, and perverts all equity, and causeth Justice to stand a far off, and lets the evil doer go free, and punisheth the innocent that walk in the Law of God (which respects no mans person) and are subject also to every Ordinance of man for the Lords sake: him do I witness against, that acts these things contrary to all equity, without respecting his person;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.27.</note> yet no power do I resist, but in that dwells, which suffers all things, hopeth all things, and am subject to the will of God: in whom I have that peace which the world cannot give, nor take from me: praised be the name of the Lord for ever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <p>ANd for witnessing the truth, which here I am called to declare: as the Lord directed me by his Spirit do I now suffer imprisonment. And that they may be made manifest, whose souls are not subject to the higher Power, nor to the Ordinance of man for Conscience sake; I shall declare the cause, and manner of my imprisonment, and the cause and manner of the imprisonment of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduk Stor<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and their proceedings against us, at the two last General Sessions, holden the 13. day of the fourth month.</p>
               <p>Vpon the 15. day of the first month in the year 1654.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115968:14"/>I being at a peaceable meeting of the Lords people in a friends house in <hi>Wellinborough</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire,</hi> as I was exhorting them in the name of the Lord, there came in <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Denit,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Hackney</hi> Constables in the said Town, and with them <hi>Henry Smith</hi> and <hi>Richard Beacons;</hi> and as I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the Truth, <hi>Henry Smith</hi> did oppose it; and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables by force did take me forth of the meeting, and would not shew me their Warrant, though it were often desired of them; and that night they carried me before <hi>Thomas Pentlow</hi> of <hi>Wilby,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.17.14.</note> who is in Commission to do justice in the County of <hi>Northampton:</hi> And after he had examined me, he said unto me, that if I would go home and live with my wife, and go towards her the next morning, I should have my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. I answered, I do not stand in my own will, but in the Will of God, and can make no such promises, not knowing what the morning will bring forth; and then (though none could lay any thing to my Charge that is the breach of any Law) he did commit me to the Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles till further Order, and on the seventeenth day of the aforesaid Moneth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 23.10.</note> they carried me againe before <hi>Thomas Pentlow,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Browne</hi> of <hi>Kettering,</hi> who also is in Commission to do justice, and joyned with <hi>Thomas Pentlow,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Andrewes,</hi> and <hi>John Boddington,</hi> whom the world calls teachers being there present, did very much stir up the Rulers against me, and by <hi>Thomas Andrews, Robert Beeton: Richard Barnes,</hi> and <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> was I accused to be a wanderer, that had left my wife and calling, and to be a rayler, because I declared the truth, and desired <hi>Thomas Andrewes,</hi> (on the third day of the 10. month, at the steeple house in <hi>Wellinborow,</hi> after their publik worship was ended) to prove his doctrine and practice by Scripture, but he fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and would not stand to prove his practice and that which he had spoken. The truth which I had declared I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed not: but to be a wanderer I did deny, and I told them my habitation was in the Lord, and that I was in that calling whereunto he had called me, &amp; that I had also an habitation on the earth, where my wife lived and was not burthensom to any: then <hi>Thomas Pentlow</hi> asked, how I could make that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115968:15"/>appear? I answered, that I had a friend at the dore, if he might be admitted to come in, without offence, that could wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness the truth, of what I had declared; then he was by <hi>Thomas Pentlow</hi> admitted to come into his house, and being examined he did declare the truth according to what I had said; and then the Rulers being stirred up by those called Teachers, who sought to insnare him in his words instead of hearing the truth in my behalfe, did take offence at him, and did examine what his name was, and where he dwelt, and what his occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation was, and wherefore he came into these parts; to which he answered that his name was <hi>Marmaduke Storr,</hi> and that his dwelling was at <hi>Ringbrough</hi> in <hi>Holdernes,</hi> in the East parts in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> and that his occupation was a Farmer of grounds on which he grazed Oxen, and he told them the cause of his coming into this Country was to visit his brother <hi>Ioseph Storr,</hi> whom <hi>Thomas Pentlow</hi> had cast into prison at <hi>Northampton,</hi> and to supply his wants. And he further said that he was to go into <hi>Staffordshire,</hi> to take his Farm againe of <hi>Thomas Brown,</hi> Trustee to one called Lady <hi>Skevinton,</hi> the terme of its time being out within eight dayes, which did occasion his coming the sooner into these parts: then <hi>Thomas Pentlow,</hi> asked him what he had to do in that place, he answered he hearing that I was accused to be a vagabond, and he knowing the contrary did come to testifie it, and he alledged that he did not come into his house without his admittance. Then <hi>Thomas Pentlow</hi> asked him if he would take his oath of what he had declared concerning me;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.30. <hi>and</hi> 37.</note> but in obedience to Christ who saith, Swear not at all, he refused an Oath: then the Ruler being stirred up by <hi>Thomas Andrewes,</hi> who did accuse us as <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Jesuites,</hi> and dispersers of dangerous principles; and they all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving we would not swear, after they had confulted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; for a snare, they tendered to us the Oath of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration: but we both for Conscience sake refused to swear in obedience to our Lord Jesus Christ, who saith, Swear not at all,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.12.</note> and the Apostle <hi>James</hi> saith, Above all things my brethren Swear, not neither by heaven nor by the earth neither by any other Oath but let your yea he yea, &amp; your nay be nay, least you fall into condemnation. And we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115968:15"/>being like-minded to the <hi>Apostle,</hi> lest we should fall into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, refused the oath: but we did in the presence of the Lord God renounce &amp; deny the things renounced &amp; denied in the form of that oath, &amp; all Principles contrary to the Spirit of truth, which gave forth the Scriptures: then they told us, they looked upon us to be persons disaffected to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and did require us to find sureties, to be of the Good behaviour, and to appear at the next Sessions to be holden for the County of <hi>Northampton;</hi> but we replied that, of our good affections to the Common-wealth, we have given Testimony in assisting it with our persons and estates in the time of its greatest straits, but to lay in sureties to be of good behaviour we did deny, except they would read to us a Law, that declared any thing that we had done, or that they charged us with to be evil behaviour: they said that they was Judges and didjudge it so to be. We answered that if they were Judges, they ought to judg us according to a law, and desired them to read us a law, by which they judged us to be of evil behaviour,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 21 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2, 13.</note> we knowing in our own consciences, that we had not misbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ourselves: but they would read us no law to convince us as transgressors, but made a <hi>Mittimus,</hi> and sent us to prison the 17 day of the foresaid month, a copy of which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed us by <hi>Iohn Snart</hi> Joaler, and in prison we was kept, until the General Sessions which was holden on the 25, day of the 2. month 1655. where there sat <hi>Henry Bartlet, Iohn Mansil,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Thornton</hi> who was in Commission to do justice, and when we was called to the barr, they read the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ttimus,</hi> as a Charge against us: but <hi>Marmaduke Storre,</hi> declared and doth declare, that what they charged us with, is false every word, as concerning him; but only he did refule to swear, and not any man appeared that did or could accuse him of his evil doing or the breach of any Law either by word or action: but they put him joyntly in the <hi>Mittimus</hi> with me, who came on my behalfe to witness the truth, though they can accuse him of nothing else but what is here declared; and they accused me of some things they pretended to be spoken, above ten weeks before he came into this Country, but not any witness did there appear, to prove that which they accused me for: neither could they read me any Law, that those things they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115968:16"/>accused me for, was a transgression of; but those that should have done justice according to equity, instead of so doing did again require us to find Sureties, to be of good behaviour, and to appear at the next Assises; but we did refuse to lay in Sureties, except they would read us a Law, which did declare us to be transgressors, or of evil behaviour: which they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and did again commit us to the common Goale, where we continued, until the 13. day of the 4. Month at which time we was brought before the general Sessions, where there sat <hi>William Butler</hi> of <hi>Oundle,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.9.</note> John Mansil, Iohn Thornton,</hi> and one <hi>Ward</hi> of <hi>Hoton,</hi> who were in Commission to do Justice, and with us before them was brought <hi>Thomas Cocket</hi> whose dwelling is at <hi>Dingley</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire,</hi> whom <hi>Iohn Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Brown</hi> cast into prison, the 15. day of the second Month, when he went before them on his servant <hi>Edward Fermans</hi> behalf to witness that he was no wanderer, but did labour hard with him in his Calling, which is making shoes; and we being called to the Bar, they commanded us to put off our hats, but we stood in the Faith of our Lord Jesus Christ,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iaui.</hi> 2.1. &amp;c.</note> and in obedience to the Law of God, which respects no mans person; Then they said, that we affronted the Court, with standing with our hats on. We answered, that neither the Law of God, nor the Law of the Nation did require us to put off our hats; and we told them, that we did not keep them on in contempt, but for Conscience sake. Then <hi>Robert Guy, Clark</hi> of the peace did affirm, that to stand with our hats on, was a transgression of the Law of the Nation; and <hi>William Butler</hi> said, it was evil behaviour; We desired them to read us that Law that did declare standing with the hat on, to be evil behaviour, or that did require any such thing as putting off hats; but they refused to read us any Law, and said to us, we tell you that it is a transgression of the Law, and evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour to stand with your hats on: and we do require Sureties for the good behaviour. We answered, we do not refuse to lay in sureties to be of good behaviour; Then <hi>William Butler</hi> (who is also an Officer in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) said, We will not be so much your servants, for you are unworthy fellowes; and, said he, You do put
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115968:16"/>confidence in the Army: but I tell you, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army will be more severe in punishing you, than any have been yet. But we answered, That the Officers of the Army, under whom we had faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully served in the late wars, ought not to punish us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law; Then <hi>Robert Guy</hi> laid unto me, that there was information given, that I had made disturbance in the Countrey: I answered, that the persecuting gene ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did in times past so accure <hi>Paul,</hi> to be a ring-leader of the Sect, and a mover of sedition throughout the world, who turned the world upside down; Then <hi>William Butler</hi> said, that <hi>Paul</hi> were falsly accused; but thou art really such a one.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 17.6.24.5.</note> I desired him to prove that I were such a one: then he said that we was unmannerly people, in standing covered before them. I answered, he that respects persons, is in the evil manners, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresseth the Law of God, and <hi>Marmaduke Storr</hi> said that they who sat to judge us, ought not to be our accusers, and we desired, that our accusers might appear face to face, that if we had transgressed the Law, we might suffer according to the Law: but no information was read a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any of us; neither did any appear that did or could accuse any of us of evil doings, either by word or action: But those that sate to judge us, told us, that we was idle disorderly persons: we desired them to prove it before the Country; and I said to them, that my Calling was to declare the truth, which should be witnessed in all their Consciences, at the dreadful day of God; and <hi>Mar ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke Storre</hi> said, that when he was committed, he had the managing of grounds of about seven score pounds a yeare, on which he grazed Cattel, which could not be managed without labour; and he further told them that the occasion of his comming into the Country, was to visit his Brother in prison, and that when he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he was upon his Journey to have taken his farm again of the owner of it, and he profered to let them see a letter under the hand of him that did let it, to testifie the truth of what he said: but they refused to look on it, and told him that he was a wanderer, and an idle
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115968:17"/>person: And <hi>Thomal Cocket;</hi> in answer to their accusing him to be an idle disorderly and wandring person, said to them, that his outward welling (as some of them did well know) was but twelve miles off, in the same County, and that he did labour hard in his Calling, and he desired that he might have the benefit of the Law, and if any could accuse him, he desired they might there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to his face, and he was ready to answer the Law, but not any appeared, that could accuse him of evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; then they instead of judging our cause in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, did manifest the secrets of their hearts, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to be silent, and heare the Sentence of the Court, which is as followeth, Gaoler, put them in the house of correction, and suffer not any people to come at them, and suffer them not to have any meat brought to them, and suffer them not to have either pen, link, or paper brought to them, but keep them strair, and work them hard, but no time they prescribed, how long we should be there continued; but the Goaler accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Command, took us away, and put us in prison,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10.</note> where we remain numbered among transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors; and for the truth sake, that innocency may be clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the aspersion of the wicked; and that all those that are sober minded, who have an eye to see, may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider and discern,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.12.</note> and with the light of Christ, try and judge, whether these men have not proceeded unjustly against us, and through envy and cruelty perverted the Law, and abused their power committed to them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their own Oaths, Protestations, and former promises of liberty, when they with us was persecuted by the late enemies of the truth, who fell before this present power that now is, which these men profess, that by vertue of that power, these have passed the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned sentence, which makes them manifest to be more cruel, then those that fell before them, or then any hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenish.</p>
               <p>Magistrates we read of in Scripture, or then ever <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi> was against the <hi>Israelites,</hi> who did not forbid them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115968:17"/>food, when he commanded them to be holden to hard labour: and their sentence is also contrary to the Doctrine of Christ, which is to seed our enemies that hunger, and to visit those that are sick, and in prison; but they in stead of so doing, do imprison the innocent, and gives command that none shall visit us, or bring us food.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. &amp; 25.43. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20</note> O what will you do, that dare to profess the name of Christ in words, whose practice this is, when he comes to look for fruit: whither will you fly, when Christ shall say, <hi>I was in Prison, and you visited me not;</hi> and What you have done to the least of these that believe on me, you have done it unto me. Read your portion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40. and 41. <hi>Go ye cursed into everlasting fire;</hi> and now all people who fear God, and know the liberties of this Nation, consider whether they be not here infringed by these men, who contrary to Law, do imprison men up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their lawful Travel, and take them from their Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and imployments, and then falsly accuse them to be idle, and upon that account order them according to the sentence formerly written: <hi>he that hath an eye to see, let him see.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now a few words to thee <hi>William Butler,</hi> who art an Officer in the Army, and boasteth in the arm of flesh, and sayes, that the Officers of the Army will take a more severe course, in punishing us whom the world in scorn calles Quakers, then heretofore hath been taken. I say unto thee and to the rest of the Officers, whom thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares openly upon the bench, would severely punish us: take heed how you requite the Lord, evil for good, who for his anointed sake, hath reproved Kings,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cho.</hi> 16.20.21, 22.</note> and hath in your eyes appeared the God of Armies, who hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown the Horse &amp; his Rider, and take heed how you oppress his people least the Lord God of Hosts cut you off in his displeasure, as he did the Oppressors,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that he destroyed before you. And learn thou of him who is meek, and low in heart, that thon mayst know, that no Officer of the Army ought to punish a peaceable harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less people, that transgress no National Law, but walks
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115968:18"/>in the Law of God, which is without respect of persons; for he that is a Souldier, ought to do violence to no man, nor to accuse falsly, as thou didst us in saying that we put confidence in the Army, which is false; for our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is in God, who is the Rock of ages.</p>
               <p>And now a word to all you into whose hands, power, is committed to judge between man and man, who turn your power against God, and persecutes his faithful ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and are offended at them, for standing with their hats on, before you.</p>
               <p>Consider what that is in you, that is offended at us, for comming before you with our hats on, seeing neither the Law of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.14.</note> nor of the Nation requires it; but on the contrary, the Law of God saith, that he that respects persons, commits sin; and we for conscience sake, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put off our hats at your Commands, no more than <hi>Mordecay</hi> could bow to <hi>Hamans</hi> will, though the King did command it, and though his life, and the life of all the Jews,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.9.</note> young and old, throughout the Province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> was indangered to be destroyed, because he dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed the Kings Command: yet he regarded it not, but gave up himself to his people, as you may read, <hi>Esth.</hi> 3.2. chap. 6. &amp; 13. chap. 4.14. chap. 7.10. &amp; chap. 9.7.5. And he stood in the faith &amp; obedience to the Law of his God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5.6, 7.</note> as we do now, who cannot disobey the Law of our God, in respecting your persons at your Command, though our Relations, Liberties and Lives, be ingaged as you now rule by your wills contrary to Law, and our God is the same God, that destroyed <hi>Haman,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered <hi>Mordecai</hi> and his people; and he will seitter you, who trust in the arm of flesh, and in his own time will deliver us, by the arme of his mighty power, in whom we trust who is now arisen and will judge our cause in righteousness,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.4.5. &amp;c.</note> and render tribulation to them that trouble us, and to us rest, with all dear Saints of God, who was hated and penecuted of the world, when the Lord Jesus shall be revealed from heaven, in flames of fire, to render vengeance upon all you that know
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115968:18"/>not God, and are disobedient to the Gospel of Jesus Christ, though you make a profession of him in words, while you are filling up the measure of your forefathers iniquity (the Bishops and unjust Rulers) who persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the truth as you now do, that upon you may come all the righteous blood,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.34.35.</note> of those faithful Martyrs and witnesses of Jesus Christ, that hath been shed in your generation or birth, from the beginning unto this day: and you have gotten their words to trade, and paint your selves with, as the Jews did, the true Prophets words, and made a faire outward profession, with gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing the Sepulchers of the righteous, as you do now, with crying up the Ordinances of Christ, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Christ, and sayes, If you had been in the dayes of your forefathers,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.47.48, 49, 50, 51.</note> you would not have slain the Martyrs that died in Qu. <hi>Maries</hi> Raign; but we say unto you, they suffered by the same murthering spirit, which you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest to be in you, who persecute by her Lawes, and do imprison, and falsely accuse (under the name of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, seducers and disturbers of your peace) the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Servants of the Lord Jesus Christ, whom he hath called forth of the world, and made conformable to him in his death, through the sufferings and renewing of the spirit in the Regeneration. And this we declare to you all, that do act these things before mentioned,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</note> and yet makes a profession of faith in Christ, that they who did in times past, or that do now believe in Christ Jesus, and are regenerate and born again through faith in him, are no persecuters, neither did they, nor do we who believe in Christ, persecute falsly, accuse or imprison, any that speak in the name of the Lord, and exhort people to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and we do again declare, in the presence of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, and it shall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered with the light in all Consciences, that you that do imprison, falsely accuse, persecute, and scorn those that declare against sin in your streets, and in your Steeple-houses (under the names before mentioned,)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115968:19"/>are shut out from amongst all the Saints and Children of God, that believe in the Lord Jesus, and you are found in <hi>Cains</hi> way, who slew his Brother, and in <hi>Ishmaels</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture born after the flesh, which birth is the same that crucified Christ, stoned <hi>Stephen,</hi> and put to death his faithful Ministers and witnesses in all ages,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ga.</hi> 4.29. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. from the 32. to the end, and the 12.1.2.</note> who some of them had no certain dwelling place, and others wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered about in Sheep skins and Gote skins, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute and afilicted, and counted the off-skowring of all things by the world, who was not worthy of them, who did indure tryals of cruel mockings, and was beaten and imprisoned, as we are that suffer by the same seed of evil doers, and they was slain with the sword, and quenched the violence of the fire, and were tortured, not accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliverance, but did rather chuse to suffer, what man did do unto them, than they would transgress the perfect Law of their God, who had called them out of the world;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.2.</note> and these are our Cloud of Witnesses, and their God is our God, and will deliver us, and render to you every one of you according to your doings, and with what measure you meet to us, it shall be measured to you again; and you shall not escape, but shall receive at the Lords hand the Cup of the wrath, and fury of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, which he will fill unto you: and will get his glory upon you,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.8.9, 10, 11.</note> in his righteous Judgements, except ye repent: therefore speedily return to the Lord, and walk in the light of Christ Jesus, that reproves for sin, least you perish in your gainsayings, and your hearts be hardened, so that no more place of repentance be found: therefore now while you have time prize it.</p>
               <p>And all dear Brethren and Companions in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</note> and patience of the Lord Jesus, who are his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful witnesses, lift up your heads, and rejoyce in the Lord, who hath counted you worthy to suffer for his names sake,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9.</note> and stand unmoveable in the light, life, and power of God, and be bold and of good courage, be of a sound minde, and be obedient to the Lord Jesus Christ, and forget the things that are behinde, and press
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115968:19"/>forward in the pure light through the strait gate, in the daily Crosse to that which is contrary to the light, and tread and trample upon that which would shake your confidences, and be faithful to the end,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb,</hi> 10.35.37.12.28.</note> that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a full reward (with all the faithful ones, who suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered before you) from the Lord God of Sabbaths, who is a consuming fire to his enemies, but is, ever was, and abides for ever, the Refuge of all that trust in him:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Psal.</hi> 9.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> glory and prayses be given to him for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>From the righteous seed, whom the world in scorn calles</hi> Quakers, <hi>whose bodies are in outward bands, in the common Goal in</hi> Northampton.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>